Inventory to the John J. Stephan Collection 1932-1978
Hoover Institution Archives
John J. Stephan collection
1932-1978
86025
Stephan, John J., collector
3 manuscript boxes, 1 phonorecord (1.2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Photocopies of trial transcripts and other legal documents; photocopies of surveillance reports and internal memoranda and correspondence of the United States State Department and Federal Bureau of Investigation; and clippings, printed matter and photographs, relating to activities of the interwar emigre Russian fascist organizations Vserossiiskaia Fashistskaia Partiia (led by K. V. Rodzaevskii in China) and Vserossiiskaia Natsional-Revoliutsionnaia Partiia (led by A. A. Vonsiatskii in the United States). Used as research material for the book by J. J. Stephan, The Russian Fascists (New York, 1978). Includes some correspondence of Stephan.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1986.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Russians in foreign countries; Fascism--China; Fascism--United States; United States--Politics and government; United States--Foreign relations; China; Russia; Vserossiiskaia Fashistskaia Partiia; Vserossiiskaia Natsional-Revoliutsionnaia Partiia; Rodzaevskii, Konstantin Vladimirovich, 1908-1946; Vonsiatskii, Anastasii Andreevich, 1898-1965; Phonorecords
Container List
- Correspondence with the illegitimate son of Anastase Vonsiatsky dealing with the life of his father. Includes a photo of the son, death certificate of Anastase Vonsiatsky, and a photo of Japanese lover of Anastase, Fusako Nakamuro (still living - prominent writer in Japan)., Anastase Vonsiatsky was Vozhd' (leader) of Russian Fascist Party, American Branch, 1933-1941. The source of the funds used by Vonsiatsky to finance his activities was his wife, Marion Ream, an heiress whose father founded 22 corporations, including Nabisco, Ream Reinsurance Co. (Folder 1: 1)
- Vonsiatsky's 1934 world tour (Folder 1: 2)
- On the world tour: goes to Harbin to meet with Konstantin Vladimirovich Rodzaevskii, Head, All-Russian Harbin Fascist Party. Tried to unite parties and failed. Rodzaevskii executed in Moscow in 1946. (Folder 1: 3)
- Japanese and Western material, published and unpublished, on Russian émigré activities in Manchuria, 1924-1939. (Folder 1: 4)
  Includes Japanese Imperial Archives August 25, 1939, top secret report on White Russians in Manchuria.
- Vonsiatsky's correspondence with Edward J. Hickey, Commissioner of Connecticut State Police, offering to help put down mill strikes, 1941. (Folder 1: 5)
- Putnam, Connecticut: Vonsiatsky's newspaper clippings from Fashist 1935-1941. (New York Public Library has a full run.) Vonsiatsky claimed he published it underground in Moscow. (Folder 1: 6)
- Published complaints about Vonsiatsky, 1934-1941, in newspapers including Daily Worker and Pravda (Folder 1: 7)
- Complaints about and investigations of Vonsiatsky including complaints to State Department (Folder 1: 8)
- U.S. Immigration investigates Vonsiatsky (Folder 1: 9)
- State/War/Justice departments' investigations, 1935 (Folder 1: 10)
- State Department investigations, 1934, 1937 (Folder 1: 11)
- FBI investigations (Folder 1: 12)
- FBI investigations (Folder 1: 13)
- 1939 investigations (Folder 1: 14)
- Vonsiatsky's 1941 depositions registering Russian Fascist Party as a foreign agent (Folder 1: 15)
- Bigamy file. In 1920 he married Liuba Muromskii in Sevastopol and never divorced her. In 1922 he married Marion Ream. (Folder 1: 16)
- Vonsiatsky: life and activities, including Vonsiatsky's impression of Herbert Hoover 1932. Vonsiatsky and Novoe Russkoe Slovo. Includes postage stamps that Vonsiatsky had printed with his portrait to be used after he took over the Soviet Union. The Russian Bear, his restaurant. Includes copy of Horst Wessel Song with Russian words. (Folder 1: 17)
- British intercepts of German-Manchurian cables, 1941, code named Bermuda. Public Records Office 1941 intercepts of cables going from Harbin to Warsaw, Connecticut to Warsaw, Shanghai to Warsaw, etc. discussing topics such as how Russian fascists would divide up Russia after their victory. (Folder 1: 18)
- Ream family correspondence (Folder 1: 19)
- Offprints on Russian fascism (Folder 1: 20)
- Article by Oberlander on All-Russian Fascist Party and correspondence (Folder 1: 21)
- Correspondence of John Stephan with National Archives (Folder 1: 22)
- Xerox of a Hoover Library 1935 publication, Rodzaevskii's Azbuka fashisma (Harbin) and advertisements for Natsiia, theoretical journal of Rodzaevskii's Far East Russian Fascist Party, and other Russia Fascist publications (Folder 1: 23)
- Rodzaevskii's trial depositions, Moscow, 1946. Includes material relating to Major Shun Akikusa, a Japanese intelligence officer in charge of Russian émigrés in Harbin. He was also executed in Russia.) (Folder 2: 1)
- Rodzaevskii's trial and execution (Folder 2: 2)
- Photographs (labelled on back) (Folder 2: 3)
- Maps of Harbin used in Professor Stephan's book, The Russian Fascists: Tragedy and Farce in Exile, 1925-1945 (New York: Harper & Row, 1978); maps of Vonsiatsky's estate (Folder 2: 4)
- Photos not used in book, including Harbin street scene, Fascist school (Folder 2: 5)
- Photos; some are duplicates of previous (Folder 2: 6)
- Photos, including White Guard leaders in Harbin (Folder 2: 7)
- Negatives for all folders (Folder 2: 8)
- Volumes I-III of transcripts of Vonsiatsky's Hartford, CT trial, 1942. Includes index of trial. (Folder 2: 9)
- Volumes IV-V (Folder 2: 10)
- Volume VI-VII (Folder 3: 1-2)
- Volume VIII (Folder 3: 3)
- Vonsiatsky's 1942 trial: newspaper accounts (Folder 3: 4)
- Prison file. (He was sentenced to 5 years in 1942; served 3.) Includes medical record from penitentiary, Springfield, MO. (Folder 3: 5)
- FBI informants. The Kurt Molzahn Case, including Alexius Pelypenko, double agent (Folder 3: 6)
- U.S. State Department: establishment of diplomatic relations with USSR in 1933 (Folder 3: 7)
- Russian fascist publications from Vonsiatsky's press, ca. 1935-1940 (Folder 3: 8a-8c)
- Nazi links with Russian fascists from SS archives (Folder 3: 9)
- Trial of German-American Bundists and Vonsiatsky, July 1942. (Folder 3: 10)
  (Vonsiatsky was already in prison from other trial.)
- Letter from sister of Rodzaevskii, N. Rodzavskaia, 1962, to J. Stephan; Review of J. Stephan's book by Valerii Vulkov in Oktiabr, 1993; and "Preliminary list of Russian Fascist Publications Held at the Museum of Russian Culture in San Francisco" (Folder 3: 11)
- Sheet music for the audio recording, May 1935 (Folder 3: 12)
- Microfilm of Russian fascist émigrés in Switzerland (Folder 2)
- Sound recording of the party anthem of Vserossiiskaia Natsional-Revoliutsionnaia Partiia led by A. A. Vonsiatskii, 1935; 10-inch, 35 RPM disc. Use copy reference number: 86025_a_0006625